Abraham: Even in the most
efficient well-run companies,
teams can be affected by conflict.
This may involve a clash of team members
over their contributions to a shared
project or team leaders who have battled
over their positions with managers who
don't see eye to eye with them or simply
a clash of personalities within the team.
Whatever the source of the
conflict, it often involves a
breakdown in communication and
trust and can cause resentment.
Conflict should be addressed before
it gets out of hand, and this can
be done using proactive strategies
as conflict often starts with small
disagreements that escalate fast.
Nicole: So, what are the signs
of conflict within a team?
Things that can suggest conflict
are the members of the team’s
body language, facial expressions,
and tone of voice in discussions.
Team leaders and managers who know
the team members should be able to
spot any changes in the team dynamic.
Abraham: What can be done to resolve this?
Using an intermediary or trusted
third party that both sides can
have faith in, can help with
resolving conflict by being fair and
impartial and identifying the issues.
By remaining objective they can give
everyone involved the time and opportunity
to present their own perspective on
events associated with the conflict.
Dominant individuals should not
be allowed to bully more reserved
members of the team, and everyone
should be able to have their say.
Nicole: Let's look at what
process should be followed.
First, team members should be
spoken to individually and each
should be asked the same question.
They should also be made aware that
all discussions are confidential.
Individuals should be allowed to put
their points of view forward in their
own time without making assumptions.
Once the intermediary or facilitator
understands the different perspectives,
then they need to bring the different
parties together and encourage them to
discuss the issues between themselves
in a calm and non-confrontational
manner, giving opportunity to listen
to and respect each other’s views.
If the conflict affects the
whole team, then this discussion
should involve the whole team.
Once the grievances have been
aired then a plan should be drawn
up to detail and agree on actions
for resolution and reconciliation.
This should be followed up by
getting feedback on how things
are progressing going forward.
Sometimes by airing the grievances
that may have started the conflict,
things can be resolved quite
amicably to suit all parties.
If, however, a resolution to the
conflict cannot be reached, then
formal procedures may need to be taken
and disciplinary action may follow
depending on the nature of the conflict.